so let's compare update and invalidate
coherence approaches we will compare
them for different things that the
applications often do here we will say
what the update protocols are gonna do
and here's what an invalidate protocol
is going to do if the application has a
burst of rights to one address and if
that address is shared then each write
will send an update in an update
protocol this is bad because each update
results in competing for the bus so it
creates bus contention and also it
consumes energy and makes write slower
in an invalidate protocol only the first
right will send out an invalidation and
the remaining writes are just gonna be
cache hits that don't result in any bus
traffic that is good why would an
application do abrasive writes to one
address well because when we are
computing something we may need to
update it several times until we get to
the final result another common behavior
is when an application writes two
different words in the same block for
example when we are initializing the
block we will write to every word in
that block if that block is shared an
update protocol will send an update for
each word that we write that is bad
because it means that one cache line
worth of writes might result in
something like 10 updates in an
invalidation based protocol the first
write that we have is gonna invalidate
the other copies and then the remaining
accesses to the block to the same or
different words are gonna be just cache
hits that don't result in bus traffic so
this is again good for the invalidate
bad for the update and the final
scenario we will consider is the
producer-consumer scenario where one
core keeps writing data and another core
is supposed to read it in this case for
the update protocol the producer will
send updates every time it modifies the
data and the consumer then finds the
data in its cache for example if there
is a buffer the first pass through the
buffer will put it in the cache and then
reading the buffer keeps it in the cache
and here writes are gonna put new data
in the buffer so that the consumer just
keeps getting it from its own
- this is not great the producer sends
updates but it's kind of the best we can
do because the data really has to get
from one place to the other so this is
about as good as this scenario gets in
an invalidation based protocol however
the producer will do a write that
invalidates the readers copy so when the
reader the consumer wants to read it's
gonna be a cache miss and it has to get
the data from the writer and then a new
write will happen and invalidate the
copy and so on so this is about as bad
as it gets for this scenario because not
only do we create bus traffic when we
invalidate we then have to have a cache
miss and have another bus operation to
get the data so as we can see from this
table update and invalidate based
protocols have different advantages so
which one do we choose in practice well
it turns out that all modern processors
use the invalidate type protocol but not
exactly for these reasons as we can see
invalidate based protocols have some
strengths and some weaknesses overall
they tend to be slightly stronger than
update on average but that's not really
the knockout punch that makes them win
handily what really makes them win with
no contest is when a thread moves to
another core so a thread was using one
core and then simply the operating
system decides to move it to another
core so what happens in the update
protocol is that it now will keep
updating the old course cache note that
our working set was in one cache now it
moved to another one but in reality the
other cache still has blocks that
correspond to our data so what happens
is all the rights that we make in a
near-future
are gonna be updating the other course
cache until that cache replaces those
blocks by running another core for
example this is pretty horrible because
a thread movement ideally what would
happen is we would just move the data
over and continue working privately on
on our private data so let's see how
this horrible scenario for updates works
when we have invalidates in that case
the first write to each of the
blocks will have to invalidate the old
copy but after that initial period there
will be no traffic anymore
so this is about as good as it gets
without actually taking the content of
the old cache and copying it explicitly
to the new cache and again this is
pretty common operating system behavior
so we really don't want it to perform
horribly and because invalidate based
protocols are commonly used we will now
look at invalidation based protocols for
the rest of this lesson